{
  "reference_number": "10998",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Action is urgently needed because the previous government tinkered with a seruious problem.. This government was elected on a\n\n platform of addressing climate change - the government should set as challenging and aspirational a target as possible."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The climate change problem is pressingly urgent. Part-measures have been tried before. This is the time to grasp the nettle and take\n radical action."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "The ETS is demonstrably a failed mechanism open to manipulation and downright fraud. Offsetting emissions does not reduce the\n\n emissions. There must be an absolute reducion in carbon emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The target should be set at a challenging level and policy settings should then ensure that the target is met. The target should be\n legally binding on successive governments."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree it makes sense to have a progressive planned approach to meeting the end goal of carbon-zero economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Emissions budgets should be changed only in order to make them even more stringent and radical. There should be an independent\n review of any such changes in order to detect 'bullshit' or fudging."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "BUT ... the ability to make changes to the emissions budgets should be very restrictive and limited within a very small range."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Government should prioritise investment in research into emissions-reducing technologies, either by direct grant or by tax\nincentives. New Zealand should aim to become a world-leader and exporter of such technologies."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "A clear programme should be provided by the Government to give guidance and certainty to private enterprise in their business\nplanning."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government should draw upon the expertise of NGOs which have been campaigning on the issue of climate change for decades\n- such as the Environmental Defence Society and Greenpeace; Academics in the climate field, progressive economists."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I(t's main function should be bullshit and crap detection. It should have powersd to set aside foot-dragging by industry resistant to\n\nchange."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The ETS should not be subject to political influence. The Climate Commission should have control of ETS policy settings. Successive\ngovernments should not be able to overrule the Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Care must be taken to ensure that appointees to the Commission are committed to radical action on Climate Change."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Bill should include mechanisms for coordinating local responses to Climte Change"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We should implement such a reporting power as soon as possible"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The need to address Climate Change is extreeme and demands urgent attention by the Government. The Government must take a\nvisionary lead on this issue, if necessary taking action well in advance of general public support levels. There are times when\n\ngovernments should lead the people and this is one of them."
    }
  ]
}
